Guide to the Richard Harvey Wright Papers, 1835-1980 and undated RL.01415
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Richard Harvey Wright papers
1835-1980 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Wright, Richard Harvey
RL.01415
151.5 Linear Feet
Richard Harvey Wright (1894-1980) was a businessman of Durham, N.C., and founder of Wright Machinery Company. Wright Machinery merged with Sperry Rand Corporation on 29 March 1957. Collection dates from 1870-1980 and comprises correspondence, 1870-1941; legal papers; printed matter; business papers; financial papers; and clippings relating to Wright's business interests, particularly the Wright Machinery Company of Durham, N.C., manufacturer of packaging for tobacco products and various other kinds of commodities. There is much information on the economic history of Durham and the development of the tobacco industry. Volumes in the collection include financial records and letterpress books for business correspondence. Later additions comprise business correspondence; financial ledgers and statements; machinery licensing, leasing, and loan agreements; and legal documents of the Wright Machinery Company. Also includes one framed oil portrait of Wright, signed "Freeman. 1922."
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Richard Harvey Wright Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1979, 2002, 2005, and 2021.
Biographical Note
Richard Harvey Wright (1894-1980) was a businessman and native of Durham, North Carolina. Founder of Wright Machinery Company. Wright Machinery merged with Sperry Rand Corporation on March 29, 1957. President of Allenton Company and Wright Real Estate, both family companies. Collection includes papers of his uncle, Richard H. Wright (1851-1929), partner of W. Duke and Son Tobacco Company and owner of Durham Traction Company and Durham Telephone Company.
Collection Overview
Collection (232,267 items; dated 1870-1980) comprises extensive files of correspondence dating from 1873-1941; legal papers; printed matter; many business and financial papers; and clippings relating to Wright's business interests, particularly the Wright Machinery Company of Durham, N.C., manufacturer of packaging for tobacco products and various other kinds of commodities. There is much information on the economic history of Durham and the development of the tobacco industry. Volumes in the collection include financial records and many letterpress books for business correspondence.
Additions (4-27-79) (2002-086) comprise business correspondence; machinery licensing, leasing, and loan agreements; and legal documents (2101 items, dated 1941-1967) of the Wright Machinery Company. Also includes one framed oil portrait of Wright, signed "Freeman. 1922."
Addition (2005-108) (65 items, 1.1 lin. ft.; dated 1877-1905) comprises one letter book; one financial ledger; a judgment appeal; general contractor reports and statements; rental statements; and checks.
Two accessions (97-087 and 97-105) containing chiefly print materials from Wright Machinery Company, including company newsletters, were separated from the Wright Papers and placed in the Wright Machinery Company Records collection.
Addition (2021-0025. 1.1 lin. ft.; dated 1835-1878) contains account and day books from Tally Ho and Durham, North Carolina. There is also a volume of "The Methodist Protestant" newspaper and "Gram's unrivaled family atlas of the world".
Related Material
Wright Machinery Company Records, 1943-1989 (most print materials were originally accessions 97-087 and 97-105 from Wright Papers)
Rubenstein Library, Duke University
Tobacco industry -- North Carolina -- Durham; Industries -- North Carolina; Durham (N.C.) -- Economic conditions; Durham (N.C.) -- History; Business records -- North Carolina -- Durham; Sperry Rand Corporation; Wright Machinery Company (Durham, NC)
- Correspondence Series, 1873-1941 and undated, 245 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  Additional correspondence (bound letterbooks from 1888-1905, 1928-1929) can be found in box 305.
  - 1873-1887 Aug. (Box 1)
  - 1887 Sept.-1889 Apr. (Box 2)
  - 1889 May-1890 Nov. (Box 3)
  - 1890 Dec.-1891 Apr. 6 (Box 4)
  - 1891 Apr. 7-1891 Aug. 26 (Box 5)
  - 1891 Aug. 27-1892 Apr. 11 (Box 6)
  - 1892 Apr. 12-1892 Dec. (Box 7)
  - 1893 Jan.-1894 Jan. 8 (Box 8-9)
  - 1894 Jan. 9-1894 Nov. (Box 10)
  - 1894 Dec.-1895 July (Box 11)
  - 1895 Aug.-1896 June (Box 12)
  - 1896 July-1897 Jan. (Box 13)
  - 1897 Feb.-1898 Feb. 20 (Box 14-15)
  - 1898 Feb. 21-1899 Feb. (Box 16-17)
  - 1899 Mar.-1900 Feb. 14 (Box 18-20)
  - 1900 Feb. 15-1901 Feb. 8 (Box 21-23)
  - 1901 Feb. 9-1901 Dec. (Box 24-27)
  - 1902 Jan.-1903 Mar. 11 (Box 28-30)
  - 1903 Mar. 12-1904 Jan. (Box 31-33)
  - 1904 Feb.-1905 Jan. 20 (Box 34-36)
  - 1905 Jan. 21-1906 Jan. (Box 37-40)
  - 1906 Feb.-1906 Oct. (Box 41-43)
  - 1906 Oct. 30-1907 June (Box 44)
  - 1907 July-1908 Jan. (Box 45-46)
  - 1908 Jan. 23-1908 Dec. (Box 47-50)
  - 1909 Jan.-1909 Dec. 15 (Box 51-54)
  - 1909 Dec. 16-1911 Jan. 24 (Box 55-59)
  - 1911 Jan. 25-1911 Dec. (Box 60-64)
  - 1912 Jan.-1912 July (Box 65-69)
  - 1912 Aug.-1912 Dec. (Box 70-73)
  - 1913 Jan.-1913 May (Box 74-78)
  - 1913 June-1914 Jan. 18 (Box 79-83)
  - 1914 Jan. 19-1914 Nov. (Box 84-90)
  - 1915 Jan.-1915 June 21 (Box 91-94)
  - 1915 June 22-1916 Jan. (Box 95-99)
  - 1916 Feb.-1916 Dec. (Box 100-107)
  - 1917 Jan.-1917 May 23 (Box 108-111)
  - 1917 May 24-1918 Jan. 3 (Box 112-115)
  - 1918 Jan. 4-1919 Jan. (Box 116-122)
  - 1919 Feb.-1919 Dec. (Box 123-128)
  - 1920 Jan.-1921 Jan. (Box 129-136)
  - 1921 Jan. 12-1922 Jan. (Box 137-143)
  - 1921 Apr. 20-1921 May (Box 144)
  - 1922 Feb.-1922 Dec. (Box 145-150)
  - 1923 Jan.-1923 Dec. (Box 151-156)
  - 1924 Jan.-1925 Jan. (Box 157-162)
  - 1925 Feb.-1925 Feb. (Box 163-167)
  - 1925 Dec. 28-1926 June (Box 168-171)
  - 1926 July-1926 Dec. (Box 172-175)
  - 1926 Dec. 28-1927 July (Box 176-179)
  - 1927 July 14-1928 Jan. 20 (Box 180-183)
  - 1928 Jan. 21-1929 Jan. (Box 184-189)
  - 1929 Jan. 15-1930 Jan. (Box 190-195)
  - 1930 Jan. 9-1930 Nov. (Box 196-201)
  - 1930 Dec.-1931 Dec. (Box 202-208)
  - 1932 Jan.-1933 Jan. (Box 209-214)
  - 1933 Jan. 11-1934 Jan. (Box 215-221)
  - 1934 Feb.-1935 Mar. (Box 222-225)
  - 1935 Apr.-1935 Dec. (Box 226-228)
  - 1936 Jan.-1937 Jan. (Box 229-233)
  - 1937 Jan. 12-1937 Dec. (Box 234-238)
  - 1938 Jan.-1941 Dec. (Box 239-242)
  - Undated (Box 243-245)
- Legal Papers Series, 1879-1949 and undated, 11 boxes
  Additional legal papers can be found in box 270.
  - 1879-1893 (Box 246)
  - 1894-1901 (Box 247)
  - 1901-1906 (Box 248)
  - 1910-1915 (Box 249)
  - 1915-1919 (Box 250)
  - 1919-1925 (Box 251)
  - 1926-1936 (Box 252)
  - 1937-1949 (Box 253)
  - Undated (Box 254)
  - Undated estate papers (Box 255)
  - Patents, circa 1930 (Box 265)
- Printed Material Series, 1835-1945 and undated, 12 boxes
  Series includes a variety of printed matter including machinery advertisements and instructional guides, military recruitment materials, and international machinery catalogues. Additional printed materials can be found in box 272.
  - Print materials (Box 256-263)
  - Print materials (Box 302-303)
  - Gram, George F., "Gram's unrivaled family atlas of the world", 1883 (Box 306)
  - "The Methodist Protestant" newspaper vol. 2, 1835-1836; 1 volume (Box 307)
- Financial Papers Series, 1890-1950 and undated, 37 boxes
  Series contains all financial records for Wright's companies, including Durham Traction Company, Wright Real Estate, Wright Machinery Company, and Allenton Company. Additional financial papers (financial record books) can be found in box 304. Box 269 also contains photos.
  - Financial papers, circa 1920 (Box 264)
  - Financial papers (Box 266-301)
- Memorabilia Series, 1944-1945 and undated, 2 boxes
  Series includes cigarettes boxes, photographs, blue prints, and calendars.
  - Collection of vintage cigarette boxes (Box 304)
  - Oversize photographs, blueprints, calendars (Box 305)
- Manuscript Volumes Series, 1875-1943 and undated, 174 volumes
  Series includes bound volumes consisting of correspondence, accounts, and journals.
  - Letterpress books, 1888-1934 (Volume 6172-6257)
  - Account books, 1901-1933 (Volume 6258-6259)
  - Address books, 1917-1927 and undated (Volume 6260-6261)
  - Album of parts of four-pocket stamper, undated (Volume 6262-6265)
  - Durham Traction Company Auditor's Report, 1907-1911 (Volume 6266-6268A)
  - Cash books, 1889-1932 (Volume 6269-6274)
  - Day books, 1893-1929 (Volume 6275-6278)
  - Journal, 1929-1932 (Volume 6279)
  - Day book, 1922-1923 (Volume 6279A)
  - Index, undated (Volume 6280)
  - Invoice books, 1901-1922 (Volume 6281-6284)
  - Journals, 1889-1943 (Volume 6285-6298)
  - Invoice book, 1901-1922 (Volume 6299)
  - Land book, 1891 (Volume 6300)
  - Ledgers, 1890-1934 (Volume 6301-6320)
  - Index, undated (Volume 6321)
  - List of patents, 1892-1909 (Volume 6322)
  - Economy Packing Machine Company minutes, 1898 (Volume 6323)
  - Order book, 1910-1919 (Volume 6324)
  - Record books, 1887-1930 (Volume 6325-6329)
  - Rent books, 1906-1933 (Volume 6330-6336)
  - Stock certificate Book, 1887 (Volume 6337)
  - Time book, 1890-1891 (Volume 6338)
  - Deeds book, 1891-1892 (Volume 6339)
  - Cash book, Tally Ho, North Carolina, 1875-1880 (Box 308)
  - Index (Box 308)
  - Day book, Tally Ho, North Carolina, 1876-1877 (Box 309)
  - Day book, Tally Ho, North Carolina, 1877-1878 (Box 309)
  - Account book, Durham, North Carolina, 1875 (Box 309)
  - Account book, 1875-1878 (Box 309)
- 1987 Accession, 1928-1980 and undated, 3 boxes
  Addition (1-21-87) is an unprocessed collection of company records grouped by topic. Personal records in Box 3 include correspondence between Wright and his wife, Helen, military papers for J. D. Wright, and obituary articles for Wright and family.
  - Company records (Box 1-2)
  - Company records (Box 3)
  - Personal papers, 1 folder (Box 3)
- Oversize Material, 1 folder
  - Oversize Material (Box 3, Folder 1)